A Guide to the Augusta County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1746-1912
Library of Virginia
- 1813-085: James Logan vs. Molly~, etc. -
  The bill and affidavit describe the birth of a bastard mulatto child named Molly to a convict servant woman named Rose Fitzgerald, in Albemarle County in 1762 and 1763. The child, Molly, was bound by the parish to Joseph Kincaid until she reached the age of 31. Robert Logan bought the time of the Molly, and when Robert Logan died his son James Logan inherited the time. James Logan let her go free when she turned 31. He sold the time of two sons, Marcus and Andrew, Molly had while she was bound to Logan to Moses Cawood of Washington County. In Washington County, Molly sued Logan for false imprisonment and damages, alleging she had never been bound legally to Joseph Kincaid, and she sued others for the freedom of three sons, Marcus, Andrew, and Joe. The jury awarded her damages and loss of time she had been legally confined, and on behalf of her sons. Logan appealed to the District Court but the court record from Washington County couldn't be found. The District Court reversed the decision concerning the sons, but not Molly, costing Logan 700 dollars. Since that time, Logan found a witness, Andrew Greer, of Carter County, TN, who married a daughter of Joseph Kincaid, and Logan is now suing to stay the proceedings at law. Logan wins the case, and doesn't have to pay damages.
- 1814-060: John McClenechan vs. Nester Harden -
  Case pertains to a land warrant granted in return for military service in the company of Charles Scott, present Governor of Kentucky, on a "Cherokee expedition" organized by Francis Fauquier in 1760. Several plats of land in Randolph County.
- 1814-072: William Coleman vs. David Richardson etc. -
  Case involves patents given to soldiers who fought under Washington in Braddock's War (French and Indian War). Contains numerous copies of land warrants issued to soldiers for their service in that war. Case also involves adjustments of claims to unpatented lands in the counties of Monongalia, Yohogania, and Ohio, 1783.
- 1814-097: William Stoneham, free man of color, vs. Administrator of George Stoneham -
  Plaintiff states that George Stoneham, in his lifetime, emancipated several of his children of colour, of which plaintiff was one, after a period of 6 years, to give him time to pay off claims that might be made against, them and to give them time to learn an industry to enable them to better make their way through the world. Deed of emancipation was made in 1806; George Stoneham died in 1807. Administrator is the son-in-law of the deceased.
- 1815-028: Audley Paul vs. William Cochran, Jr. -
  Bill describes an effort to arbitrate marital discord by two neighbors, who draw up a separation and alimony agreement.
- 1815-030: Frederick Idle vs. Philip Gaines etc. and other suits heard at the same time -
  The suits relate to a dispute between Idle, who brought a slave named Hagar to Virginia from Maryland in 1787, when she was a young girl, and Gaines, who bought rights to her from Idle's step-children, and debt. Case hinges on the location of the oath Idle is alleged to have signed when he brought Hagar to Virginia from Maryland. Idle accuses Gaines of trying to steal the oath he signed when he imported the slaves into Virginia, and petitions to have the suit moved from Grayson to Staunton; also accuses Gaines of trying to have Hagar liberated, so he won't have to give her up to Idle to pay a debt. Exhibits include record of charges of assault and battery made by Hagar against Frederick Idle. Numerous depositions. She sued on grounds she had been brought into Virginia illegally in 1787 by Philip Gaines, one of the defendants, in violations of the law passed in 1785 to prevent the importation of slaves. Court upheld the Grayson court finding that Hagar was a slave, and ordered Gaines to deliver her and her children to Idle, as found in the detinue (order to return property) issued by the Grayson County court.
- 1812-059: Andrew Anderson vs. John Fulk -
  Plaintiff is a free man of color suing to get his wife back. His wife was taken in payment of a debt.
- 1815-091: George Baylor vs. Mathias Link, etc. -
  The suit includes a plat showing a diagram of pipes for carrying water to a distillery, a sawmill, and a meadow.
- 1816-074: Admr. of George Stoneham vs. Henry Stoneham -
  Many years before the death of the plaintiff, he formed an illicit connection with a woman of color his own slave by whom he had a number of children. The defendant states that the deceased left little or no estate except the female negroes aforesaid and her children all of whom he emancipated.
- 1817-014: William McCampbell vs. Heirs of Benjamin Borden, Sr. etc. -
  The bill of complaint of William McCampbell represents that a certain James McCown purchased from Benjamin Borden Sr. deceased four hundred acres of land, part of his large survey of 92,000 acres. A certain James Trible who then acted as a surveyor in the county surveyed the said tract of land, beginning at white oak on the Southside of a Timberwidge turning thence North ten degrees West one hundred and sixty poles to a black oak, thence South seventy six degrees East four hundred poles to a post by a Hickory sapling, thence South fourteen degrees East one hundred sixty poles to a post, thence North seventy six degrees West four hundred and ten poles to the beginning. The surveyor in setting down in his field notes the second course of the said survey, through mistake as your orator alleges insisted the letter N instead of the letter S so that the course according to the abbreviation manner usual with surveyors, would read North seventy six degrees East instead of South so many degrees East. The error not being discovered at the time of your orator alleges a deed was written in which the said second course was inserted according to the error aforesaid.
- 1818-043: Robert Lewis vs. Nelson Barksdale and James Minor -
  Robert Lewis made a contract with a certain Nelson Bardsdale acting as agent for a certain James Minor for the purchase of a slave by the name of Will. The orator charges that the slave was represented and warranted to you to be of good character and that in consequences of said warranty and agreement to deliver the negro to him at the plantation in Albemarle Co. The orator charges that since the said contract, he received a report from the neighborhood from whence he was brought that he was a slave of most infamous character, he being a notorious nuisance, a rogue and other issues too tedious to mention.
- 1818-061: Solomon Ritchey (free man of colour) vs. Frederick Painter -
  A certain Frederick purchased of a Walter Frazer a tract of land 160 acres and agreed to pay therefore to Frazer the sum of $168.00. The sum of money according to a contract with Frazer, applied to your orator to advance him of money for that purpose and promised your orator that he would give to him as his security of the said money due him advanced, 45 acres of the aforesaid tract of land. The orator thinking he would be in so doing although ignored in such matters, he did advance toward the payment of the land $147.00 as will more fully, be appear by the article, etc.
- 1818-099: Gdn. Of John Edmondson vs. Exr. of John Edmonson -
  Case contains a chart documenting the hiring of slaves belonging to the estate of John Edmondson in 1810. Chart includes the name of slaves, as well as family information such as "son of"; to whom hired, securities, and sums.
- 1819-010: James Craig vs. Peter Moore -
  The suit concerned a valuable stud horse named Soratis.
- 1819-014: President of the College of William and Mary vs. Alexander Herring
  The defendant being appointed surveyor for the county of Rockingham with a reservation in his commission to the said College of the sixth part of the legal fees that should be received by the said defendant and having at the date aforesaid given his bond according to the Act of Assembly in such cases made and provided conditioned for the faithful payment in October of each year of one sixth part of all his fees and profits for surveying and conditional also to render to the Treasurer of the college for the time being a true and faithful account upon oath of all surveyors, stops and times made by him the said defendant or his deputies and what fees the parties employing him should pay which bond is hereto annexed as part of your orators bill of complaint and in conveyance. The said defendant proceeded in the executor of his office and your orators further show unto your honor that your orator some years ago instituted their suit in the honorable court and obtained a decree for the amount of fees due to the said college up to the 1st. day of July 1805, which decree did not embrace the fees for surveyors made under orders of court all which will more fully appear reference being made to the proceedings in the suit which your orators refer to. Your orators further show unto your honor that since the 1st day of July 1805 the said defendant hath rendered no account lot even of the surveys performed by him or his deputies which is contrary to equity and good conscience.
- 1819-025: Moses Hart vs. Robert Houston and William Davidson
  The orator lost his pocket book on the highway and he thinks he had seven hundred and thirty dollars and bank notes. Two or three days after losing his pocket book, he set up several adventures in the neighborhood, of which he has marked as exhibit A. The pocket book was found by the Robert Houston. The said Robert was seen to pass along the road on which the pocket book was lost very early next morning and is the first person who was seen to pass. The said Robert has been known for years to have very little money at command and to have had his property sacrificed at sheriff and constables sale for want of money, etc.
- 1819-085: Joseph Gray and wife vs. Margaret Blaine, etc.
  Your orator and oratrix Joseph Gray and wife, that your oratrix Margaret is the daughter of William Blaine and Margaret Blaine of Ireland. The said William Blaine was lawfully married to Margaret Blaine whose maiden name was Stephenson and had by her two daughters to wit your oratrix Margaret and Nancy Blaine married to one James Hannegan. Many years ago, William Blaine, from the same cause with which your orator and oratrix are not well informed, left Ireland leaving there his wife and her sister and migrated to the United States. The said William eventually settled in the town of Salem. After coming to this country, he married a woman named Elizabeth Thompson. His wife, the mother of your oratrix then living in Ireland and continued to live with the said Elizabeth Thompson until her death which happened about three or four years since about eighteen months since the said William Blaine married Elizabeth Hook with whom he continued to live until his death which happened last year. Your orator and oratrix state it as a fact which they are able to prove that as the time of this marriage with Elizabeth, his first wife Margaret was still alive and living in Ireland and known by the said Blaine to be alive. Your orator and oratrix would show unto your worship that the said Elizabeth Hook pretending to be the wife of the said Blaine has taken possession of his real property in and near the town of Salem consisting of houses and lots and between fifty and sixty acres of land.
- 1820-013: Samuel Cunningham vs. James McNutt etc.
  The orator (blacksmith) who was at the time an overseer of the poor took an apprentice a boy about seven years old named James Davis. Davis lived with your orator about two years as an apprentice, but was too young to learn anything of the trade, not being large enough even to blow the balloons. During this time, he was clothed and fed by your orator and treated with kindness and gave him attention. Davis started running off into the neighborhood and loitering about from place to place staying away from home for several days and nights. In order to break him of this vicious practice, your orator frequently threatened the boy telling him that the bears would catch him. At length, your orator would whip him.
- 1820-036: John Taber vs. John Beasley, etc.
  The plaintiff purchased a mare from the defendants only to find out that the mare was blind.
- 1820-039: Exr. of Mary Mackey (alias Mary Little) vs. William Mackey
  Your orator represents that the said testatrix, besides other property, left a chest, in which were deposited various papers belonging to herself and also various papers belonging to the estate of John Mackey deceased of whom she was executrix and of which she had the custody as such besides some lien of the property of said Mary. There was also deposited in the said trunk a sum of money belonging to Mary. The said chest at the time of Mary's death was in her dwelling house. Shortly after Mary's death, William Mackey took possession of the said chest, together with the papers linen and money and removed the same from the house and still has it in his possession.
- 1820-054: William and Thomas Henry (free men of color) vs. Andrew Moore, etc.
  Slaves to be emancipated and set free.
- 1820-071: Mathias Swink vs. Silas H. Smith
  Smith who became the master of John Darsinger an imported white servant and a native of Germany who in 1818 was bound by indentures to serve Smith for three years. In the month of March of the same year, Smith sold the servant to Swink for 100 dollars.
- 1821-023: John Morris vs. William Cravens, etc.
  A free negro named Sampson is codefendant. He asked Cravens, a Methodist minister, to purchase his wife and a male child, both slaves, from Smith Loffland. Sampson agreed to work for Cravens to pay off his debt to Cravens. Sampson's wife and child were held by Cravens as collateral. According to Cravens, Sampson worked off the debt. Cravens promised to take Sampson and his family to a free state should he move. Cravens planned to move to Indiana/Illinois and take Sampson and family with him. Sampson became indebted to John Morris prior to the move. Morris sued Sampson for repayment of debt. Morris visited Cravens informing Cravens of Sampson's debt. Cravens said that Sampson would repay debt but Sampson's wife and child were Cravens property and he was going to take them to Indiana/Illinois. Morris claimed that the Sampson's wife and child were the property of Sampson and not Cravens. Morris issued execution on Sampson's child Fanny for her to be sold as a slave by sheriff to recover his debt. Cravens' nephew John Cravens bought Fanny before Morris could. Morris claimed John Cravens did so unfairly and with William Cravens consent. Cravens claimed his nephew did it on his own initiative with no encouragement by William Cravens. He was out of town at the time of sale. After being purchased, Fanny "disappeared and that she is probably at this time in the state of Indiana." Cravens claimed that he was the owner of Fanny and not Sampson; therefore, she should not have been sold to repay Sampson's debt to Morris. Cravens stated that the only reason he purchased Fanny was to grant her her freedom. His nephew accomplished this objective by removing Fanny to a state "where a slave was never known." Cravens agreement with Sampson was fulfilled and no longer claimed Fanny as his property. Cravens acknowledges that the only reason he purchased Sampson's family was to secure their freedom.
- 1822-080: William Wilson vs. Thomas Mayberry, etc.
  Suit surrounds the purchase of property in Botetourt County by Mayberry and Weaver from Wilson for the purpose of establishing an iron works business. References to Retreat Furnace, Etna Furnace, and Union Forge. Backround info on the iron works. Defendants claim to have been defrauded. Property was not as advertised.
- 1823-070: Andrew Lammie vs. Thomas Tate etc.
  Case involves a title dispute for land surveyed by the Loyal Co. The original bill of complaint refers to James Anderson, who settled on Cove Creek, a branch of the North Fork of the Holstein, 1770 or 1771 and was killed by the Indians in the year 1774. Contains 5 plats.
- 1824-015: Isaac Freeman (a slave) vs. Exrs. of James Boyd etc.
  Freedom suit. Isaac was the the son of a free negro named Derry Freeman and a slave to John Milles of Botetourt County. Derry attempted to purchase his son's freedom but did not have sufficient funds to do so. He convinced John Beale to purchase his son from Mills. Derry would then purchase his son from Beale. Beale died and Isaac became the property of Beale's widow. Derry still unable to raise funds to purchase his son. Derry died leaving a will which is found in the suit. In it, he directed his executor James Boyd to procure the emancipation of Isaac. Isaac claimed that there were more than sufficient funds from his father's estate to purchase his freedom, but Boyd failed to do so although he wanted to. Boyd died. Isaac suing Boyd's executors and Beale's representatives in order to get the 450 dollars necessary for his freedom. Court judged in Isaac's favor. Isaac was represented by a negro named Hannah. She asked questions to white deponents on behalf of Isaac.
- 1831-019: William Weaver vs. Thomas Mayberry
  The dissolution of the partnership of Weaver and Mayberry that owned the iron furnaces Buffalo Forge and Etna Furnace. The main issue in the case is the ownership of eleven slaves, some of whom were valuable iron workers.
- 1832-042: Peter Bolinger vs. George Kaylor, etc.
  Bolinger, the father of a "seduced" woman, sued the man who supposedly debauched his daughter - the father paid jail fees for 12 months because the accused man refused to post bail.
- 1833-026: Admr of Harriet Parks vs. Exr. of William A Washington, etc.
  Includes information regarding General George Washington's estate settlement.
- 1834-041: Reps. of Joseph Borden vs. John Bowyer, etc., Levi Branson vs. Robert Harvey and wife, etc., Robert Harvey and wife vs. Levi Branson, etc., Benjamin Peck vs. Robert Harvey, etc., Heirs of John McDowell vs. Heirs of Benjamin Borden, Stephen Trigg vs. Robert Harvey, etc., John Paul, etc. vs. Benjamin Borden, etc., William McKenny vs. Stephen Trigg, etc., James Houston, etc. vs. Heirs of Benjamin Borden, John Calbreath, etc. vs. Levi Borden, etc.
  These ten cases concern a land grant of almost 100,000 acres, between Lexington and Staunton, given to Benjamin Borden after the 1705 law which forbade purchase of more than 4000 acres. Borden, a land speculator, was one of the few entities allowed to purchase such a large acreage. The land was purchased at some point in the 1730s. Included in the collection are 67 plats.
- 1839-007: John N. Hunter vs. John Brooks
  Case involves the sale of a Negro woman named Matilda 22 years old (along with her 2 year old child) was considered to be "defective" because she was given to having "fits" or "hysterical incidents."
- 1840-023: William Cochran vs. James Donathan
  Case involves a free colored man (Cochran) suing James Donathan over a plot of land he purchased and for the title deed to the land. Donathan apparently sold the same land to an Abraham Smith; the case involves Cochran efforts to get the deed.
- 1844-042: Daniel Webster vs. Exrs. of David Hanger etc.
  Case of Daniel Webster (a former slave but a "freeman of color"). Slave in 1834 in the Commonwealth owned by David Hanger, requesting 300 dollars Hanger had left him in his will. Webster purchased a slave girl from L.L. Stevenson named Eliza with permission of his master Hanger. "Your orator is well aware the said girl became the property of his master, but his master had always permitted your orator to retain and treat said girl as his own property, ever since her purchase by your orator of Stevenson." Hanger sold Webster to John N.C. Stockton for $550 with the agreement that Stockton purchase Eliza as well. Also Webster could earn his freedom from Stockton after working for him for a certain period of time. Webster agreed to the transaction on the condition that he would receive his freedom. Stockton purchased Webster and moved to Florida. Stockton died before emancipating Webster. Before his death, Stockton refused to give Webster evidence of his freedom until they returned to VA. Stockton's heirs refuse to grant Webster his freedom. Webster won his freedom in Albemarle County court in 1840. Copy of suit used as exhibit. Hanger's executors refuse to give Webster the 300 dollars claiming Webster was a slave at the time of Hanger's death in 1837. Webster argues that although he was legally free in 1840 he was in fact free in 1835 or 1836 based on the agreement between Hanger and Stockton; therefore, he should receive the 300 dollars. The defendants claimed that the reason Hanger sold Webster to Stockton was because Webster attempted to poison Hanger in an effort to gain his freedom sooner. Hanger no longer concerned if Webster ever gained his freedom. Webster lost the case.
- 1845-015: Admr. of Andrew Moore vs. Reps. of John Stuart, etc.
  Reference to Louisiana Purchase in suit and its negative impact on property values in the western mountains.
- 1847-003: John Bridget, a slave vs. Exrs of Susan Wayt
  Freedom suit. Slave Manumission as recorded in a will by Susan Wayt. Freeing of John Bridget, Jeff, Martha, Ann. The will states that Ms. Wayt wanted her "servants" freed, given the sum of 800.00 and should be "permitted to reside in some other state of the Union. Pennsylvania or some other state of the union where such difficulty may not exist or to the Colony of Liberia."
- 1849-023: Tapp Teter vs. Daniel Faber
  Tap Teter a free man of color and Daniel Faber were business partners in a blacksmith business. Mr Teter believed he was being taken advantage of by Mr. Faber. Mr. Faber was cheating Mr. Teter out of proceeds for his portion of the work in the business.
- 1849-024: Archibald Trotter vs. John H. Bates
  Personal property suit involving Archibald Trotter who purchases a workhorse from John H. Bates, "the mare promptly decides not to work" for Mr. Trotter. The mare is described as wild and dangerous and will kick! This is why Trotter wanted his money back.
- 1851-037: Thomas Johnston vs. Sam, a slave
  Johnston sues Sam, a former slave to the Johnston family, for repayment for supporting Sam after he purchased his freedom.
- 1855-034: Heirs of William Broughton vs. James Holderby, etc., Charles Morgan, etc. vs. John Savage, William Coleman, etc. vs. Simon Morgan, etc., Heirs of John Williamson vs. David Spurlock, etc., William Coleman, etc. vs. David Spurlock, etc.
  During the French and Indian War, George Washington led a regiment of Virginia soldiers in the Battle of the Great Meadows, also known as the Battle of Fort Necessity, which would become Washington's only military defeat. After the battle, the soldiers were given a land grant that would become known as the Savage Grant in 1772 when Virginia governor John Savage made the grant legal. As commanding officer, Washington was in charge of surveying the land and directing the portions to which claimants were entitled. A letter written by Washington in 1772, not found in the suit, details Washington's involvement and his desire to be finished with the situation. In 1772, the interested parties were supposed to meet to divide and distribute the land. Very few of the recipients actually inhabited the land. They either sold the land to third parties or the land was taken away due to lack of improvements. The suits involve heirs who say their ancestors never received the land to which they were entitled. There are no decrees included in the case.
- 1857-068: Admr. of Joseph Jamison vs. Maria L. Jamison (alias Mariah L. Jamison) etc.